reality is existence is it has a nature
it is what it is it has an identity
right human beings have an identity we
don't get to choose our ultimate goals
we want life we want health we want
beauty we want intimacy these are
built-in we can attribute those to a god
or not we certainly have been built up
in the stories of that he's unwilling to
budge on the story of the individual
hero sam harris is unwilling to budge on
the distinct nature of science and what
it means to build our stories on science
or not to build them on science both
they are fixed willing to budge unless
they can create unless they can
co-create yeah a frame that recognizes
both of the places with they're
unwilling to budge give both of them
value and then play with them right
right play with them so Sam why is it so
important to you
Jordan why is it so important to you
let's actually find out the value
underneath Sam you've got this
incredible intellect rather than arguing
with him about terms argue with him
about why it's important
yep that way you might find that in the
end Jordan
backs out of his central conclusion
because whenever he's really pressed one
says there's a game what is the game
science empirical data yeah he's saying
there is no secular morality there's
this thing called a P Aryan game like
what the pyridine game is secular
morality that's what it is you can't
lose that argument and say that you
can't have a secular morality right
right right
like now Sam Harris challenged him on
that ask him how a pata game is
different than a secular morality answer
like ask
him the questions to get Jordan to
actually are 10 speak no one challenges
him down to the core
[Music]
hey throw what do we want to talk about
so I wanted to talk about
mr. Jordan B Peterson yeah you and I
haven't spoken about him for a while
yeah yeah and it seems that every few
months he just grows in stature in a way
that you know back when we were just
watching his psychological lectures
before he got on the scene well yes oh
wow this dude's awesome and now it's
like holy yes this is the phenomenon
that he is the the boldness with which
he speaks the the topics he takes on
right I'm working on this bringing light
to the intellectual dark web project
frame and so I want to have
conversations with you and I'm going
into the twelve rules of life going
through the chapters and I want to work
on that with you right and so I just
wanted to set some context context so
it's it's June 15th 2018 right he's
essentially a year and a half 18 months
ago he had ten thousand YouTube
subscribers
he had no patch yep yeah yep
in fact I remember you sent me it was
Owen Shoei he didn't even talk about him
and you sent me some random little note
who's like hey do you get distracted
watching Jordan Jordan Jordan Pederson
videos I'm like this is like a year and
a half before he had that that breaking
thing with the woods
c16 I think when he went on on video and
then he exploded it's been a trip
watching him yeah and and you could say
as a as an EIN rand freak as a Rand ride
as I call myself right the his
concentration on myth
yep right is such a different angle on
which to triangulate this thing called
consciousness life humanity optimum
living values rationality yep like how
do we be a self with other selves in
service of something in this context we
call life and then what is the thing
that we're calling life like this like
that you know looking at it from a
perspective of how do i articulate this
how do I find a framework which is you
know I seek lack of a better term a
rational definable generated in language
but consciously articulated set of
frames that you can use such that when
you interpret the world your life you it
causes you to make better and better
choices more and more thriving this is
the and so and then he comes out of from
now no no let's take this Union Joseph
Campbell mythic story perspective let's
take narrative and not in terms of the
narratives you create but the narratives
you inherent yeah and the narratives
that we as a culture have refined over
the course of centuries or thousands
perhaps even tens or hundreds of
thousands of years yeah what what is the
nature of those stories in this
archetypal piece not what do we create
given that we inherit that yeah but what
is the inheritance yeah yeah
and it was just encountering that
integrating that but now he's bringing
that and now there's all kinds of really
smart people who I enjoy and respect who
are commenting on him yeah and I don't I
don't know if you remember on my optimal
human values site project I went through
Sam Harris's the moral landscape yeah
right and used his fundamental
as a context in which to define a set of
optimal human values yeah right but it's
a rational like like let's look at this
and abstract out from experience not
let's take an archetype and figure out
chaos and order and the dragon and
terror and tyranny and and the hero yeah
yeah and so like the play between Sam
Harris in Jordan that fascinates me and
just what how he shows up in the world
and how the world is responding to him
yep I thought it would be fun just to
find out where you're at in that
conversation and just do our thing so
that's my intention for this
conversation yeah yeah and I bet I'm I'm
I think here I've been excited to talk
with you too about about some of the
recent slack you know flack he's been
getting for me even people that would
like we know around it who previously
really liked him who are now having like
criticism of him and stuff and like a
lot of the responses right from people
to what he's doing right both positive
and and and negative and I have to say
that like the one of the things that
I've appreciated about him well first of
all I don't think he knows exactly what
he's doing right like I don't know if he
thinks he's doing something but I think
he's kind of finding it out as he goes
but the thing the thing I've appreciated
about him is and I'm glad I have this
perspective from having watched him
before all this when I go back and I
watch an old interview of him or an old
left him or something he's exactly the
same like he shows up and he's the in my
experience he is he has the same
emphasis he has the same thinking
something out but now it's like
literally he's having a dialogue almost
with the entire world and this is what I
think it's really interesting to me is I
think it's like it's highlighting the
possibility of
of because I because a lot of this is
happening over social media so happening
over you look primarily YouTube right
and podcasts but primarily to and I was
thinking about well like we still don't
know what what the hell the internet
really is right like we still don't even
know exactly what it is but I think if
we look at it like it's a it's a
collective mind of some kind right I
think we can like we can we can we can
put a metaphor like that and we could
say that like Peter's in a certain sense
is he's a consolidation of a particular
voice that spoke something that was true
but unarticulated great and he in talent
and now he's creating kind of a new
neural net and then all of a sudden like
you know who'll be going along and then
they'll get it an interviewer or
somebody that like like you know is just
shitty with him or more like bashes him
or something like that and it's what's
it and this is what I think is really
kind of what it's cool about the
Internet or a really good thing about
the Internet is that his first response
often is kind of like you can kind of
tell it's like he's kind of irritated
right or like and rightly so I could get
it and and a little bit grumpy or
something like that and I saw some kind
of interview like like like that a while
ago and then I went and saw him speak in
San Francisco and it was like a month
later and he had basically taken that
situation right and he had brought it
into his thinking and he was working it
out right like to the crap out that was
being video that was having comments on
it and I'm watching him like it's almost
like I'm almost watching the world
thinking in some way right like he's at
first it's kind of a crash and there's
like a like a conflict and then he he
actually kind of goes huh well what is
this like and he has more Congress and
you see him working it out with people
and he takes it seriously and he's
opened
being affected and impacted and then
watching and then watching him on stage
work that out and I thought about this
I'm like oh my god this is this is like
I think I'm watching the possibility of
what something like the Internet can
actually be right of like a thought like
an insight is being worked out and
you're watching it go through all of its
stages and I got I so there's a few
different levels at which I'm like I'm
observing him it's like him I like his
stuff like it's competitive ideas are
challenging but there's also the medium
that is happening in there's watching
the way the world is responding and what
kind of world is revealed through that
and then watching actually if you is him
being a concentrated sight
metaphorically speaking
well maybe even technically speaking who
knows of where you're watching the world
actually think or a parts world mind
actually occur and I can I feel excited
about about that yeah I'm just like oh
like I just want to start to I just want
to start podcasts and I want to have
this conversation with you and I want to
this idea that calm people are
interested in conversations and they're
interested in long conversations of
working it out and watching them and
engaging them and that that's a thing
where it's a it's a way where I think
technology is providing something that
is is is a platform for something less
technological in the sense that like
YouTube and podcasts now that they're
disconnected from the network's don't
have to be like little five minute clips
right into they don't have to have like
a you know they don't have to shave it
down and prove a point or something like
that literally that's more technological
from what the way the Heidegger would
define it like tech me city but
technology is creating a platform for
something less technological to happen
called the meandering of a conversation
work
get out and kind of going into the weeds
of these things and it's it's that those
conversations that are starting to speak
to people thus the dark web right and
you see and all that so that part of its
really fascinating to me - cool so you
you broke it down into four parts I want
to work them back with you I think
that's a I think that's a useful
fascinating framework and I like for for
the three dimensions of space and one of
time right the four dimensions is a nice
number of dimensions through which to
look to through which to look at things
so you've got and I'm gonna do it in a
different order right is that you've got
a culture all right you've got a
collective group of people each one of
which has their own representation
they're part of a larger cultural
conversation the self that they are
comes about inside of a culture and so
it's shaped by that culture and so you
could say that it's it's appropriate to
think about each individual self as part
of a culture as long as you understand
it's not like a cell in an organism but
more like a self in in an ecology and
that self is adapted to the ecology so
we've got this ecology all of these
different parts and it's evolving as an
ecology yeah yeah yeah and then there's
this medium this technology within this
culture that's allowing for a new kind
of conversation its facilitating the
kind of conversation that you would have
if you were in person yeah like if you
were watching a conversation or if you
were taking part in a real conversation
with another live human being yeah that
conversation is going to be and it's
going it's going to unfold according to
the logic of the people involved
right right and it's not particularly
constrained yes yes right the the the
technology of communication of being in
the same location that the technological
were in bodies in a space kind of thing
is is being recreated through this
long-form interview and through this
internet piece where like you can watch
Jordan Peterson have a conversation
almost every day of the week like he's
out giving talks and he's getting
interviewed and then people are talking
about him and it was like instead of
being in a one-to-one conversation where
you're sitting in a room with someone or
you're you know you're at a party and
there's a group of people having a
conversation yeah the technology which
for awhile got us into these little
five-minute sound bites like until last
friggin week right how does in these
sound bites kind of thing we're the only
shared conversations for people who
weren't actually in the room the only
shared conversations in this larger
ecology were the ones that were managed
by the major networks yeah yeah totally
and up until literally five ten years
ago the only conversations that the
ecology shared were sound bites yep
totally and this medium we've got this
medium that allows for the kind of thing
that we used to have in one-to-one
conversation where we could meander
we've now got these ongoing
conversations which are deep and wide
and far ranging and incremental and
recursive this person talks to this
person talks to this person text and
it's like this huge party looks like
this big conversation that we can all
participate in to different degrees and
that so we've got the the culture and
then we've got this medium and that meet
the medium is causing the
culture to interact in different ways
yeah yeah and then you've got this one
person yeah speaking his perspective
uh-huh it's like he's at the party and
he's talking and people are listening to
him yes right and and what is it what
does it take to be at the front of a
room it takes an audience like I always
I always say that the first one I'm
teach work with my clients I would say
the first rule of leadership is turn
around yeah
is anyone following yeah that's the
first rule of leadership is like if you
want to Lee if you want to be a leader
you actually have to have people follow
you
it has to be able to say hey I'm talking
yeah does anyone want to listen yep
so you've got this one guy who's talking
and all these people are listening yes
yes and they're like talk more right
here here here's $80,000 a month that
we're just gonna give you to keep
talking yeah totally totally
yes right and so he's talking and he is
sharing his perspective and other people
are sharing their perspective yeah and
and in the process there's like this
kind of two levels of things going on
one all of the different perspectives
kind of get to come into the
conversation and so you're watching a
large conversation with lots of
different perspectives yeah and any
perspectives that actually speak for
other people right especially in
Jordan's case like he's saying things
and people are going I didn't know how
to articulate that yes I did know that I
actually felt and thought that thing or
some variation of that thing I mean it
was kind of subtext and I at times I
would
I feel something and then but he's
saying it and I'm identifying that that
I resonate with that yes and so many
people are doing that that he's becoming
an icon like an archetype in his own
form in this conversation if the
conversation were a plot or the
conversation were a story like he's a
character that people are identifying
with because they identify with that
character that's the kind of thought
that they think that's the kind of
concern that they have that's the kind
of mm-hm
and then other people are doing in so
now you get to watch the different
people play the things out and so the
culture through the technology and the
individuals now get to play out the
organism ecology becomes represented
into like a living play where it used to
be a dramatist would create a plot and
the actors would play out the things so
that we as the culture could watch it
but now it's spontaneous human
conversation happening at these levels
and something about Jordan Peterson that
clues into it so i'm i recited your four
areas i'm not sure if i got them right
from your perspective i I think yeah I
think you totally got it right and when
it was compelling to me and just a
little bit of a backdrop is is that I'm
so I've recently been kind of realizing
because I've been just intrigued with
Heidegger for years now and I don't
really haven't been able to tell you why
a map but I think I've recently
discovered why and it's actually part of
it part of it has to do with actually
what what Peterson was doing because
Peterson is so many ways doing something
very similar and he didn't know about
Heidegger so like after I think he wrote
his book or something like that he's
doing very much the same way of
observing things and articulating them
or engaging them in at the same kind of
level this whole thing about like
reality isn't a bunch of determined
things that's you have to work at doing
that but like reality is experienced as
phenomenological and unpacking that Reno
pack him and Heidegger do it in
different ways but essentially
they're pointing to something very
similar and I now that Heidegger a lot
of a lot of like the black notebooks and
a lot of things about Heidegger that
warrant either published or published or
translated in English have all been
translated now and so now a lot of the
things that were mysterious about
Heidegger and weird and didn't quite
connect there's a you're starting to see
people that draw out the themes and
there's a book that recently came out
it's called Otto theology and can't
remember the name of the kind of
ontology and theology yeah and he said
he it did he went in there and he talked
about he you saw the whole corpus of his
work having one thread and it had to do
with essentially it had to do with
technology or Tecna city and how
technology he was afraid that technology
was a kind of Anto theology that self
concealed itself ray in such a way that
it would conceal itself into oblivion
right artificial intelligence machine
all of the the mythology about you know
the matrix you know with repetition and
or durability being as standing in
reserved or being or conception of being
as being something that could be
optimized utilized and we're included in
that now and what he was seeking to do
was to reformat education and that's
what his involvement with the Nazis were
but he was really upset because they
were they didn't listen to him so he's
like this is it
this isn't like what what it is and then
he realized that there wasn't any
fundamental ontology but but that on top
that being never disclosed fully but it
had epochs in which it did were the
higher and the lower onto a theology
where a philosopher was able to like
speak both of them the big view and the
micro view at once and those points in
history was the unfolding of the
understanding of being and he realized
that there was no ultimate understanding
but that was the way it unfolds
and that he is antidote to Tecna city is
to through education is defined
education to reveal being in its
transcendent element right to not make
being something that we totally consumed
for our own optimization right but like
the roots don't like to educate people
and to make education be something that
actually reveals a way for being to
withdraw and to speak to us right in
that in a restore kind of a theological
relationship in a certain way so that
last bit that last pitch raises a
question for me and I am and I lost it I
lost there right that last bit so so I'm
going to talk about Sam Harris and
Jordan Peterson and Heidegger idea of
like the self or being yeah right which
we you could say reify into a self and
that self is part of the use it's like
how does this self allow us to move in
the world given the nature of the world
and so we're optimizing the self for use
in the world and in the process the self
that we create gets bounded in its use
and disconnected from the being yes yes
and that you like that that enclosure
gets concealed yes yes as just this and
it loses connection with this and the
way that it does it is this is all there
is and so it conceals that it's
concealing yeah yep an example of that
he would say it's like where he saw that
it The Epoch be a particular epoch that
were in what he's calling
tecna's to be right or the paradigm that
we're in is being as technology or Tecna
city or in framings another way it puts
it
he said that he saw it change when he
saw what happened with the Nazis to do
with the Jews he's like we went he said
we went from subject object where the
subject the canteen thing alike would
like or the Cartesian thing where the
subject is trying to overcome the object
or its dominance and he said like when
he saw the thing with the Jews where
they like took away their name put
numbers on them and exterminated him
he's like in that moment like what was
the understanding that even made that
possible right and he's not talking
about technology as technological things
he's not like it he's not
anti-technology what he's pointing to is
the understanding of the category of all
categories that then influences
everything inside of that category which
is being he's saying switched to a
technological point of view or ethnicity
and so what's interesting to me okay
about about this thing about like the
medium in which people aren't like like
Jordan Peterson and Sam Harris and all
the people that were calling the dark
web now right what's fascinating to me
as technology has brought this platform
up for conversations that are that are
not mediated right they're more raw
right they're not technological whereas
like the news is a little bit more
technological it's more like okay we
have five minutes there's a purpose
right we have to make it sensational
right it's it's more like standing and
reserved optimization right whereas now
technology in this new medium is
actually created a platform for
something less complete less ordered
more meandering right more like
something untechnical to be spoken and
for people to be responding to and I
think that the word technology and
something untechnical coming together
that that's speaking to people and the
way that you're talking about it
it's it's utterly it's I still haven't
formed all my thoughts about it but it's
like I think it's really significant
thing is really significant that that
people can listen into a conversation
right and be altered by that
conversation and have conversations
about that and that that's available and
the technology allowed that for to
happen and that that's what art where
our attention is drawn and that's what's
feeding us and influencing us and more
and more people I think is absolutely
extraordinary yeah it's a it's it's a
crazy time be alive you know so many
places to go with that so emplace to go
with that I want I want to go back to
your earlier point and keep that in so
if so vocabu-larry vocabu-larry - if
we're gonna say the technology if we
want to talk about technology and
differentiate from tech Nissa t yeah
okay so for example we're using video
conferencing right video conferencing is
a technology yeah okay and within this
technology there are certain things that
are limits of the technology and we work
within the limits of the technology
right for example right now you can't
see what I'm doing with my hands yes and
because you can't see the gestures you
can't see it so that changes the nature
of the conversation that we're having
and we could say the technology has
constraints to it and within those
constraints certain things live and
certain things go away yeah yeah now for
vocabulary purposes would it can we go
with the idea that the technology is the
actual thing the limitations of the
medium that were
and what that facilitates or doesn't
facilitate is the Tecna City I and I
would say yes and let me work that a
little bit I think it's also if we say
that those limits become begin to shape
our understanding and the wiki that we
then understand and we don't notice it
that's ethnicity that's look yeah and
and that's and that's absolutely key
because you and I have these
conversations and I become aware of like
how I'm using my body just becomes less
important and so I start to adjust the
way I communicate for the parts which
within the constraints of our medium and
then that just becomes part of the
conversation and that gets forgotten it
gets concealed yeah and to the degree
that we're stuck in this it gets
concealed that it's concealed to get
back into this language okay so so the
the technology of network television and
network news yep right went from we've
got three or four major channels and
news is really one hour a day yeah yep
into the area into the era of 24-hour
cable news yep in which case there's
just more conversation and then we get
in we get into the the debate format as
the news methodology where it's like
okay let's take a hot topic let's get
people on either side they argue and now
we've got competing narratives because
it's very sticky and and that's the news
the technician that comes from the
network and the cable news network
technology the technician comes what's
happening in the world are these ideas
are competing against together and it's
a very limited set of ideas it's the
same people over and over it's the same
sets of ideas clashing and that's the
world and that's the world we're living
in the technician that comes from the
technology is this thing and now we've
got a new technology
and and I want to give props to Joe
Rogan for really opening it up yep right
yeah I've got like Tim Ferriss did some
interesting things with podcasts and
these longer but Joe Rogan just said
look I don't have a list of questions
we're going to go through it is not my
job to constrain this interview into
some kind of technician that we're all
prepared for yep totally right I am
using this technology to create an
opening which is so broad and so natural
and so meandering I love I love the use
of that it's like it allows for an
organic discovery of people actually
talking yeah and like you were talking
about with your if you think about how
Oh
pertinent this is to being a human right
think about think about your grandson
right you're when you're conversing with
them he's there's the like you could say
that you guys to get together and have a
kind of conversation and the way that
you are in that conversation the way
that he is and when it goes too far and
then you're like oh and then you laugh
or when you don't laugh and oh like
literally our character becomes shaped
in a living conversation right so it's
like it doesn't surprise me that we now
have these open forums where I think a
lot of people would say who's gonna you
know like the news the new I would
imagine the news from the news
technological understanding of things
you would asked him said like you know
if Rogen came and said listen I want to
do a show where we have like two to four
hour conversations I'm not gonna have
any topic we're just gonna I'm gonna get
stoned and we're gonna whatever they're
gonna they're gonna be like no one has
the attention for that Aurum or if
Jordan Peterson is going to say hey I
want to do a 12 two and a half hour
series on the psychological significance
and processes in Jenna
sis of the Bible like who's going to
watch that yeah okay well we live in a
longtail culture yeah yeah enough people
are gonna watch it that it actually
becomes like every time he does one of
those that gets a million views yep yep
a million views yep yeah versus how many
people want to CNN with Anderson Cooper
when he does a five-minute interview
with someone yeah let's say it's in like
a million views right uh-huh yeah it
it's crazy okay so so in this you've got
this technology the crates of techni
City you've got this culture this
ecology of culture in which we live in
which ourselves are shaped our ourselves
are optimized for the culture and we get
this self like Jordan Peterson and he's
sharing his particular perspective and
other people are doing it and people the
audience watching this because of the
technology and because of this open
forum text Nissa t people are actually
able to follow a conversation and allow
the conversation to give voice to things
and articulate the self that they are
such that they recognize themselves in a
new way
yep yep exactly right and and we've got
this thing now again getting back to to
Heidegger and this technology techni
city and we build a self and the self is
concealed education as you put it is you
can educate in the sense of we want to
teach you the skills and the fundamental
building blocks of the skills so that
you can be an optimized self in the
concealed world yeah yeah kind of like
like the technological view of Education
would be that the student is like an
empty vessel eager up the vessel in
which you pour you pour what you're
learning in and then when it fills up
you're educated right yes and the things
were gonna fill in are the things that's
that self and optimize that self such
that you can go out and be a cog in the
machine be right be a worker in the
factory be a self in the culture yep
which is concealed as if this culture is
the only way to be and the self that
we're teaching you to be a good self is
one that has taken on this structure
we've got a preformed structure we're
going to give it to you your job is to
take yourself conform it into the
structure our teachers are designed to
get people and the idea of a good
education is that when you come out of
the education you fit into the Machine
right and you have the knowledge yet
right and that can be you could say a
technological or a technical education
where we teach you to work in a factory
we teach you to be a secretary we teach
you to be a scientist we teach these
things or it can notice yeah you know
just notice implicitly like without
probably even explicitly knowing or
understanding this the way that you're
talking about notice how much order is
involved with that in a repetition right
and that's the essence of getting techni
city or in framing which is where it's
the view where the only thing that we
begin to see is that which is orderable
and optimized for immediate consumption
and yes okay and did you say in framing
yeah yeah and did that I don't know if I
totally this is a thing so I I now I now
have a peg in my mind for in framing I
have some idea that that in framing is a
way of like taking techni city and
turning it into a narrative form yep
right and if you can create a narrative
form that captures the techni city that
fits into the technology yes it takes
the culture and has the self fit into
the existing culture yes the existing
ecology which is all concealed and which
is for consumption in this
say right and natural are you it's for
use right and that's how you can be get
these awful places like Plano Texas
we're all there are are shopping malls
there's not in shopping malls and chain
restaurants like literally they're all
there is all about consumerism 40% of
the population or something is like
hooked on on opiates right it's
absolutely I go there and it's ah it's
awful if no one is like walking around
going this is this is awful it's there's
an oblivious to it we begin to not be
able to see the jump to the degree that
we have adapted ourself into the in
framing to the degree that our self
actually fits in the techni city yeah
then it becomes second nature it becomes
the way that it is and we simply work
within that framework yeah and and the
beingness and this is like because
because as I think about Heidegger it's
it's this what is being beyond that what
is being that it can be that and what
else could it be
exactly and right there what we're
saying what we're saying is that when
you confront being one of the ways that
you nub you confront being is that
there's something about it that is
withdrawn from your intelligibility or
is that goes beyond the limits of your
understanding but it shows itself or
stands forth as it is in its not being
completely revealed to your mind so for
example like like intimacy I think is
one of the places where that's still
really alive is that when people have
intimacy there is this experience of
like it's not an experience of like
collapsing collapsing distance and being
informed about but informed about the
other and in like a nap or something no
it's like you're looking at just there
and you see this human being you're like
oh my god you're you're someone you are
more than the thing that I could be
informed about that
a set of ideas of who you could be but
you were actually more than that yeah
and that intimacy with life with spirit
with like this aliveness this being is
that experience itself is more than what
we can see in our in framing from the
techni city as based in the technology
and right that or that more gives a self
that is also more than the one that you
are on your phone right great so let's
take this I want to call I want to take
the idea of world Inge yeah right right
so there's being in the world yeah right
being in the world that we encounter
being through the in framing and then
through what doesn't fit the in framing
and then we have to create a new frame
for that which we are encountering and
we world it like we world this though
the experience within the frame within
the in frame within the tech Nyssa t and
when we encounter the chaos beyond the
order of the in frame when we encounter
the chaos we have a choice we can either
demonize the chaos which we could say is
a way of taking an in framing that we
already have and the existing story
that's within our frame in which we have
within our frame we have good and bad
yep yeah and we take the we take the
ultimate other that's that chaos that
thing that doesn't fit in our frame and
we reduce it down into the evil the bad
thing within our friend yep exactly
take the fullness of the unknown of the
other and this never more true than in
relationship yep totally right never
more true than in relationship yeah the
other that vast unknown Ness of the
other yeah like you know my wife and I
10 years now yeah dating 17
like when I'm present to what is unknown
in her when I test what I think is known
and I say I think this I think you're
thinking and feeling this not like you
are thinking and feeling this aren't you
yeah but I experience you as thinking or
feeling this is that accurate does that
map for you how would you say it and
then she comes back and says this thing
which I'm like oh that is not within the
realm of who I thought you were
you have now surprised me so this chaos
I can deal with this unknown this thing
which does not fit my frame the
beingness of the world and especially as
embodied another human being another
human being represents being like
nothing else because it can speak and
yet we listen we can so there's that
beingness yeah and she appears to me she
occurs for me as in a world like I see
her and I interpret her into a known
frame yeah yeah she's in the world I am
world in her right right right that is
an action that I am doing I am actively
interpreting her as something as if the
something that I'm interpreting her has
actually encapsulate who she is yes
right like I'm taking this vastness this
unknown 'no switch is so much deeper
than my capacity to imagine her and I'm
pretending I'm world in her as if she's
something that I can know yes right and
then I'm confronted with when I'm aware
of it I'm and when I seek it and this is
the hero going out into chaos looking to
go beyond order
to go beyond order to go beyond the
tyranny of its only this and everything
that I know fits into my existing
structures yep yep that this being is
beyond my world
yes and that encountering chaos as the
hero yes yes means challenging the order
yeah versus you challenging her forth to
reveal the self saving of your own world
right like you challenge like your world
you could say that your world is
untechnical in the sense that it's given
by a horizon of unknowability that you
actually move toward right and what I
think what we're talking about and I
think this is part of what is speaking
to people about Petersons in a way that
like maybe they wouldn't put this way
but I been thinking about this is that
in so many ways the way he's presenting
life and this is where I think he's
really where I see him and in Heidegger
doing much of very much similar things
is he's presenting life in a very
untechnical way right he's actually he's
he's saying like no it's not about
optimizing yourself and knowing for sure
it's actually if you want to be alive
like handle your shit get ordered right
but so that you can stand up and choose
the KSR you're gonna move toward feel
what moves you and let the unknown grab
you and grip you like and give yourself
to it voluntarily so that the so I just
I just really I think I just as you're
talking about that I just known you
right what the question I have is when
you go there was this point where you
went
um you're in you what oh so you're like
you were top your you know just like
animating a conversation with min and
you said so it's like this right that
you said right right is speaking to some
kind of awareness that there's a being
right that is other than what you think
already
okay so there's already an openness to
you but when she says the other thing
like what what is your world like what
happens to your world right okay so okay
great so let's get back to Peterson and
cleaning your room
yeah yeah right and Peterson's entire
mysteriousness of life the thing that I
love about his what he might call his
religious perspective is that this thing
is so mysterious that to the degree that
we think that we can know it through
science we're missing something yeah to
the degree that I think that I can
understand my wife yeah like and really
get her essence I can get like I can
predict parts of her personality like I
know her well enough to guess how she's
going to respond with relative accuracy
to various kinds of things but to really
get her when she's alive the more I
clean my room in this metaphor of the
more I look at myself and notice where I
am disordered why and and I love how he
puts it he says there's things that you
know that you need to do that you're not
doing there are ways in which I know
myself my world is disordered like I'm
not handling something that I know I
ought to handle the not handling of
which causes me pain suffering and a
lack of power yep yep
if that's my room and I clean it it's
about starting with the things that I
know I can put in order and clean up so
that I then have the resources available
to me so I have the power event so I
have the alignment to push right so when
I do that I become available yeah to
experience what's new what's deeper
what's better and I become available in
two ways like I think about intimacy I
say intimacy is like I break it down
into three steps you I share something
value vulnerable I share something that
I have not worked out so thoroughly that
I'm like solid about I share something
that if and I define it that when I
share something vulnerable it's
something that if you were to judge me
about it mm-hmm it would hurt yep right
it's something about myself with this
which is sufficiently raw yeah
sufficiently unprotected sufficiently
new to my own consciousness sufficiently
new to the process of sharing that I
don't have it's not tough it's not
facile yeah so I'm sharing something
vulnerable I'm sharing something which
is actually alive for me in myself some
part of myself and then the second step
is I feel understood by you yeah I feel
like you actually get it like you know
what I'm talking about
my experience and my articulation gets
reflected through you such that I'm like
this thing that I'm experiencing
actually lives in our shared reality our
shared space so I share something
vulnerable right I feel understood like
you might understand me but if I don't
feel understood that loop isn't complete
yeah so I share something vulnerable
I can feel understood and
I feel accepted I feel that you think
that I'm a good person that I have a
reason for doing it that I'm that you
can you can understand and go yeah I get
it right like you're a good person so
when that happens when I share something
vulnerable I feel understood and I feel
accepted I'm gonna experience intimacy
and there's two sides to that one I have
to have my room clean enough that I have
enough self available that I have enough
consciousness available that I can look
into myself notice what I'm experiencing
and share it with you and I have the
courage I have the courage to share it
with you because I've got enough of my
shit in order that I can risk it you
have that I have the bandwidth available
the mental bandwidth the wood available
the mental emotional bandwidth and I
have the courage to share it that
provokes intimacy but then you have to
have your room clean enough that you can
actually give me the bandwidth to
understand me and accept me and not just
get triggered by what I'm saying and go
into your world right because I mean
what happens most often in conversation
unfortunately is somebody shares
something and instead of the other
person going oh let me see if I got that
right what do you oh you're saying this
oh I get it
oh I know you now yep I feel connect I
accept you I get it instead of doing
that right you share something with me
and I go well I don't know about that
and now I make it about me
yeah so you don't feel understood you
don't feel accepted and then I share and
then you go what well you're not
listening to me and then you and there's
no intimacy yep so when you ask me like
what happens when I listened to her from
the perspective of wanting to discover
what's new like when I when I say hey I
think feeling this is that right versus
you're feeling this
aren't you right and it's that it's that
I have cleaned my room enough that I'm
available right to discover her - yeah -
I have enough me and the desire
available to discover her or I have
enough me available that I say you know
what I want to tell you something about
me
yeah I'm going to either provoke
intimacy and intimacy is always the
feeling of intimacy is a is a world Inge
beyond being the current in framing yeah
yeah like that's what intimacy is it's
like you go deep you're going deeper
you're going into a new level of
understanding of self of connection so
cleaning your room right makes you
available to encounter being to
encounter chaos not in order to call it
evil so that you can become a self in
relationship to it and now you've got a
safe self because you made a bad guy and
the more you make the bad guy the more
you become the good guy and it's all
about polarizing against chaos by making
it into the evil dragon know you're
after the dragon's treasure yep yep
right you're out there looking for the
unknown this is why the hero's journey
is always a journey into the unknown the
beyond where there's absolute danger
because vulnerability when you share
vulnerable share vulnerably most of the
time you don't get intimacy right you
get attack right okay so now Jordan
Peterson comes out in the world and he
has been on this journey of look I want
to clean my room I I want to study the
human psyche in its ugliest places so
that I can confront it like in the room
of his psyche he's like
I want to study totalitarianism and
prison guards and and gulags and
concentration camps and and mass
murderers because I want to get into the
room of my psyche so that I can clean it
up so I can recognize Who I am and who
I'm not and now I'm here and I've got
something to say and I'm going to share
it with the world and like in a
relationship like in an intimate
relationship because of the new
technology which allows for his lectures
to go online or his long-form interviews
to go online this new thing when he
shares it's like an intimate
conversation there's this new
possibility exactly and some people go
oh I understand and I accept you yeah
and that creates intimacy between him
and his audience and so he gets people
who love him yeah yeah and and and it's
hilarious because what do they come up
they come up to him and he reports over
and over they say the most intimate
things like let me share my vulnerable
truth with you here's who I have been I
have made just shit here's the places
where I have just been ugly and but I'm
sharing it with you because I trust you
you've been into with me I want to be
intimate with you and it brings him to
tears and other people demonize yep they
polarized they become the good guy
making him bad and they project all of
the badness onto him and it's it's
infuriating
I'd loved I'd love to talk about some of
those some of those yeah yeah go go for
it thank you for letting me oh that was
awesome it like you just basically I'm
so glad you said that because those have
been kind of a morphic things that I
just read that book and I'm like oh my
god this is why I've been thinking about
everything so I just started to
articulate it with you and then you just
took it and you just did the thing like
that you were just talking about and I'm
like right so we're doing it right now
as always watching this that the so
there's a thing with it is it is it's
it's crazy like it's crazy to watch him
go on an interview where it's so clean
Stefan's like probably probably over Oh
at least over eight times that I'm I'm
aware of where it's clearly the
interviewer comes in with the position
and they already have a peg doubt and
they're trying to get him or catch him
in something and what's been cool so far
is that the jokes always ended up being
on the on the interviewer like he
they're the ones that are made into the
fool right so so far I think that's
pretty much what's happened which it is
really cool and I'm not Matt Dillahunty
perhaps being the sole exception that I
know of yeah I don't know if you've seen
that one yeah and I have something to
say greatness to and I think it has the
same thing to do with the way the
Petersons showing up in those interviews
of course there's a couple of things one
is I think right it's like I think that
that um I think that that actually
truthfully one of the reasons that if
Peterson wasn't like dark right and in
moody right into intense and I like a
boy who likes to fight cut like it and
he clearly likes to fight right it's not
like it's going in there and going like
Oh
like how come you're trying to do this
with me he's like you can you could see
there's some part of him that's getting
into it
it's totally him right and I think that
there's the wet in my what I've seen
with him is that when a nerve you comes
at him he just holds his position he
holds his position and he occasionally
steps out of it for a second and he
makes a joke about you know well be like
in the last one that I saw of him with
the woman that was like kind of nailing
him about like getting money for what he
does like you yeah just a bag he's like
well as the evil capitalist that I am
right is where he kind of points to
where they're coming from but he doesn't
ever attack them I've never seen him
attack I've seen him get frustrated
right I've seen him get flustered but
I've always seen him just talk about the
issues and where he stands right however
I think that there's something more
available and I think it was also the
case with Matt Dillahunty
because I think what he was trying to do
with Matt Dillahunty was something very
very very difficult to do but also I
think Dillahunty would have played along
with it right and it could have set the
frames in place like with sam harris
like was a paris and truth if he if he
said look i want to go into a
non-typical frame i'm not saying that
this is going to redefine the normal use
of the words but for the purposes of
this conversation let's create a
hypothetical have gone along that's a
smart guy totally totally and that's the
part that's the part about it and i
remember you saying that about him when
we were doing the first conversation
about his he's like the blotch with
harrison the first two-hour interview
about truth where they got stuck were
you were talking about like yeah you
know what i believe what you would i
recall you saying is like Jordan wasn't
accounting for how radical of a position
that he's coming in with right that if
he would have said hey like look I want
to play with this idea with you I
acknowledge and understand that this is
way outside of the normal framework
right and set that up and then like they
could have found out where they were
gone like and I appreciated that
and they think that there's the same
something in a slightly different angle
with the interviewing that our that our
people are attacking him is I think that
there's an opportunity to like call it
what it is go like pause I don't think
that that's a question like when you've
just asked me about about like how much
money I'm getting my senses that you're
actually have a position that you're
trying to catch me in is that true right
and actually unearth the thing that's
actually happening in the room right
because I have a feeling that there's an
opportunity there that's if the
interviewer then goes back into that
position and he goes like I still don't
I still don't think that you actually
relating to me as a person with a
viewpoint that has a validity that you
want to find out what that is like how
if that's true how come you're doing did
you know you're doing that like it
actually get the get the living the
living conversation up
I would love yes okay so a couple a
couple things with that one I can't
imagine why why you particularly would
want him to call attention to what's
happening including what in an inquiry
way such as you shift the level of
conversation to the structure of the
conversation and the way of being behind
the conversation and the motivations not
as an accusation but as an inquiry I
can't imagine why you would do that just
where I think it's like where I think
it's actually consistent with where he's
coming from because what does he do he's
not going let's look what's beyond the
horizon he's like let's look at the
horizon that gives our understanding
that we stand on top of and don't know
it
let's unearth it and unpack it and see
and this is the thing where you say he's
doing the same thing that heidegger's
like Heidegger worked so hard and
created this obtuse vocabulary sorry
yeah maybe it's helpful when you have
all the black books and the unpublished
stuff to matter so much to make sense of
it right but but he's attempting to
point out the horizon within which the
self exists and the things that become
optimal only exist in that optimal
context and what is the story and how do
we shift the focus from how do we move
within the story to what is the story
itself yep and yeah and Peterson is
doing that on a macro level where he
does maps of meaning like I'm telling
you it all comes down to this
fundamental story and I want to talk
about the story that we're working
within so we can figure out how the all
of the wisdom of the past can help us
navigate this fundamental story which is
part of the technology of being human
like we wake up in a body with the brain
that has must move and live and eat and
interact that's the technology and
there's a technician within that
technology which is this fundamental
story
yep total and I want to go from not from
within the story but let's actually look
at the storytelling let's look at the
story what is the horizon in which we're
working so we come we come into he comes
into an an interview with Joe Rogan and
Joe Rogan says so what's your trip and
the buter Singh goes boom boom and Rogan
goes really Wow what about this what
about and it just unfolds and it grows
because the technology that Joe Rogan is
using leus to an openness for peterson
to shine exactly so they just give his
gifts and shine but what's interesting
is it's not it's not not and this is
what makes it untechnical a lot like
what what tech technology allow for
something for something very uncool out
techni city oriented to happen is it
what's shown in Peter soon is people are
like who is this they're not like
in formed as a series of facts they're
like it's an intimate experience of
there's something going on that he's
saying that is not I can't totally grasp
but I understand in some way and then I
don't understand but the unknown part of
that actually shines out as the kind of
like chaos right that's okay yeah so if
we say that the Tecna city of network
television yeah leads to a methodology
of sound bites and those sound bites are
packaged within the in framing of the
Tecna city from the technology right
okay so now when we get to Jordan
Peterson his initial technology is
recordings of his lectures which are
open organic they're not sound bites
right not giving you a piece of
knowledge which you are going to learn
and then regurgitate at the appropriate
time he's not giving you a tool that is
that has a very specific use that at the
appropriate time you bring out that tool
and you use it he's not giving you a
world yeah he's giving you world
yes he's he's saying like it completed
you world here's how you create the
stories let's get into the technology of
how you actually create stories and and
and let's have you like here check out
this brilliant person and here's how
they thought about notice what that
makes possible for you beyond what you
already know yeah let me give you a
method a methodology for world addala G
for creating stories I'm going to give
you a best practice yeah and the best
practice is right that you have a goal
and the goal creates the facts yeah the
facts do not create the goal yes and if
you will clean your room
then you free up your consciousness to
actually discover a goal that is yours
not the goal that you inherit from the
world yeah like it's not that the goal
of being in Plano Texas is which chain
restaurant are we going to go to tonight
not optimizing in making something and
me like collapsing distances which is
that what technology does is it collapse
distances but it makes something further
away right
the thing about what's extraordinary
about Petersen is like I think I was I
was uh I've heard a bunch of people talk
about Petersen movies like look I like
his point he he's not clear on these
things I don't know where he stands on
these things
bum bum bum bum buh buh and they're kind
of criticizing him for that and I'm like
to me that's not a criticism in fact in
fact that you can't pin him down and he
can't pin him down right like he doesn't
fucking have a position on it that's
easily as he talked about like well if
you want to know what I do I believe in
God I'd sit and watch those lectures
that's what how long it takes for me to
kind of work that out and I'm still
working it out as I'm talking about it
right like that people can see that and
they're gripped by it is because there's
something real there like and I think I
loved how you put that he's like he's
not presenting a world right like an app
that you opened that presupposes you in
it and that you like lose lose yourself
into it
no he's what I heard you say is he's
he's giving world ding he's engaging you
in something that isn't fully complete
and it's it's incompleteness the unknown
speaks to a horizon that can't be fully
revealed right it's like in that sense
it's theological it's like religious and
that I think that's what he means by
religious right is that live your life
in such a way that the farthest horizon
is what shines to you right it's like
chaos that shows up to you is the thing
that you can't and then watch and like
in that engagement will is the is the
articulation of your character right it
is the making of your face right but
live in a way that like presence is that
horizon that gives testimony back to her
that horizon that makes you a veil to be
yourself that actually is available to
be gripped by what isn't immediately
intelligible to you but it's Heidegger
would say like follow the movement is
showing right and that's what kind of
being speaks in saying that I I got a
new metaphor which I'm looking forward
to how it unfolds I'm looking forward to
how it integrates into what I'm doing I
want to give it to you so so when I
think about a horizon a horizon is
relative to where you are yeah
what I'm what I got from what you were
saying is that Peterson is saying that
there is a horizon beyond your horizon
but there is a horizon that happens when
you are moving yep yeah and there's this
greater horizon which is only you can
only imagine it because it's beyond your
horizon and you can't even imagine it
because it's beyond your horizon it's
beyond the horizon of your imagination
yep and it's that greater horizon that
you orient toward us yes yes into the
degree that you don't to the degree that
that becomes something that like you
actually go bad or no or whatever it is
that doesn't have you because that's the
other thing about a horizon is that like
when you go towards it you can't ever
reach it so it's it's it's this bizarre
like it man you can think about horizons
for
years right like as when you go to its
its on some level it's an infinite
limitation it gives the ground it gives
the most certain thing that you can know
about your ground but it's what gives it
is something that can't ever be reached
in that that horizon ground experience I
think what what Peterson is
demonstrating and I think what he's
articulating and I think what he's
pointing to what Western Western
religion and judeo christianism is is
articulating is like look it's your
relationship to that horizon needs to be
one it's it's just gonna work out better
if you move toward it like you actually
you actually like don't go stop and then
and get bitter and resentful for the
limitation but you like you you let them
like the thing that can't be spoken or
seen and you orient everything towards
it and you move toward it right but but
in such a way you know that you're doing
is because in order to move towards it
it requires you to get your shit
together right and the more you get your
shit together the more you can move
towards the horizon and therefore expand
it and find new horizons and what you're
what you're focusing on is the horizon
of horizons yeah right the ultimate
abstract mmm-hmm you know integration of
the horizons that you're experiencing
yeah so- throughout the allergy and you
know i'm fond of the phrase where you
say you know if you have a quarter
there's only so many things that you can
do yeah right but if you don't have a
quarter there's an unlimited number of
things
oh man that's gonna Whittle in my mind
in the next ten years yeah and and it's
it's like this it's like once once
you're in the world of the Tecna city
once you're in the small world of the
self within the in framing yeah and and
you are you have a stock set of choices
among amongst which you choose right you
are in the world an education in this
high daguerreian sense as you're saying
is like teaching you how to make choices
within the existing world and education
is he would desire it I can imagine
which is what Peterson is doing which
I'll say which is what the dark web is
ultimately about yeah it's about
questioning the set of choices right if
there's any if there's any marks in
critique of capitalism and consumerism
that I find valuables like you talk
about Plano Texas it's like okay which
restaurant are we going to go to which
movie are we going to go to which
pre-chosen prepackaged set of options do
I choose among right right yeah and you
know Warner would say that's not a like
that's a decision what we want is choice
yeah and choice is certainly how we
relate to the existing decisions but
even more there's this possibility yeah
that goes beyond the quarter that goes
beyond which restaurant are we going to
go to yeah which show are we going to
watch on television which purse am I
going to buy which thing am I going
which status symbol am I going to invest
in next such that I can have the thing
which solidifies the self within the
yep yeah which one do you choose within
ya that there is that when I look at the
dark web when I look at Jordan Peterson
as reflected in his Joe Rogan interviews
or his Dave Rubin is also great at this
it's like okay let's create an open
space for people to actually unfold
their ideas so that we can encounter
them let's actually get intimate with
them who are they not how do they fit
into our prepackaged questions and then
you take the IQ interview or the Kathy
Newman or the vice or any of these any
of these interviews in which there's a
value to having a very specific question
and saying okay great I have a series of
three boxes which of these boxes do you
fit in Yeah right look from what you've
said you fit in this box right isn't
that so so what you're really saying is
right I'm going to take a prepackaged
world and I'm going to fit you in it
yeah I'm polarized these are the choices
you can either be this or this right and
this is the dominant frame this is what
the technician
of modern television or whatever has has
come down to you've got a certain amount
of gatekeepers who control the narrative
who control the world within which you
can show up they control the horizon and
what the dark web is doing and when you
when I look at all of the various
players in the dark web all of them are
questioning the set of options right and
and it shows up it shows up when the
interview says you better damn fit into
this box and Jordan Peterson says no
like I'm going to give you an answer
which is outside of any of your boxes
now I'm offering you a new horizon yeah
what do you do with it mm-hmm yeah and
they say no I'm gonna try to put you
back into the box and he says no here's
another horizon right I can take any box
you give me like like you said he's a
he's a boy who what likes to fight yeah
I am a boy who likes to fight it's like
yeah let's get into a conversation in
which you try to put me into a box
because I know how to take apart boxes
yep totally totally right now I'll I do
with the greater sense of humor and
playfulness than Peterson but Peterson's
under a lot more pressure than me you
know perhaps but I like to take apart
boxes he basically says look you're
trying to give me this order and fit me
inside of your tyrannical order and I
don't fit how do you like them apples
and the more they do that the more they
show up is fixed and I really like what
you're saying and call it a circling
move call it just a king of the logical
level yep in this typical interview mode
you are focused on me yeah you are
setting frames within which I answer yes
yes I'm going to switch the nature of
this game yeah and make it about how
we're conversing right right right I'm
going to include you in the conversation
not just your questions but you yeah
right and when he did that with Kathy
Newman that's exactly that was the key
he he shifted the conversation from
answering her questions to drawing
attention to the then the dynamic in the
room to the actual conversation the
thing that was happening the thing that
people are actually they're experiencing
but that wasn't the focus of the
conversation in postmodern terms right
you've got a dominant narrative and the
dominant narrative is we're in this
context where I'm asking you questions
your job is to defend yourself and it
becomes clear after
for 5-10 minutes 15 seconds that this is
not a Joe Rogan conversation this is not
a Dave Rubin conversation where
someone's actually asking you a question
and you are actually sharing yourself
with their intention to understand and
be understood and be accepted that is
not the game it is not a game of
intimacy yeah this is a game of gotcha
yeah this is a game of you fit into the
box and I have succeeded in putting you
in the box that I want you in because
that serves my agenda so it becomes
obvious at some point that that's the
game yeah everybody sees it but the
dominant narrative is that that game is
concealed we are not talking about that
game there's the world and here all the
choices within the world and Jordan
Pederson worlds yep he says how are we
world in this conversation
only what's going on here when he did
that with Kathy Newman when he did it
with oh I'm the evil capitalist yeah
right which implicitly brings in the
conversation and what and what's the
move that's being done in the
conversation right he did that in the
vice interview right he like he's he's
good at doing that and when he does that
it opens up a new world a new horizon
and this is this is the dark webs like
when I look at all the characters in the
dark web
all of them go beyond the choices
available yeah they they they actually
call attention to what is the actual
issue that we're looking at I don't know
if you saw Brett Weinstein's
conversation with sam Harris now I think
I think I started watching it and then I
got distracted I do it is epic and Sam
Harris as he's going into it just starts
asking him all of the questions
that are fraught they are the dark web
questions these are the questions that
we in the dark web are willing to
confront and he starts asking these
questions he's all well you know you can
answer this question not that it's
dangerous what do you think about the
wage gap what do you think about sex and
gender what do you think and in sam
harris is like I just can't believe I'm
doing this I'm just like leading you
down it's not the primrose path it's
like the it's like the path to hell I'm
just throwing you every question that
you could possibly lose your career over
and Bret Weinstein is like lazy hain
take it across talk boxes right yes yeah
great let me give you a real answer sir
I'm not going to fit inside your boxes
I'm gonna go outside the box yeah I'm
going to open the space of dialogue so
that we can actually talk about things
beyond the boxes of this framework yeah
and this the political political
correctness conversation with with Dyson
and Frye and the right it's like there's
this question of political correctness
political correctness from my
perspective if I were to define it using
the terms of this conversation and his
political correctness is a very tight
all right yeah it's the essence of
Tekken City yeah right it's the essence
where what we're looking to do is to
define whether or not an idea and a
person fits inside of a box and that's
where the conversation ends yes yeah
once we've got you in the box we can now
use you as a thing well we have given
you in in the worst case scenario the
like we have given you your number
we have taken away your name yep you are
now a thing your subject miss is now
gone you are an object yes in which we
will order you inside of it and show
everyone else liked you and you're done
yes and in the end the places where
Jordan has like been breaking it is when
he calls attention to that process yes
yes wait and and it ends the dark though
dark web in general the players in the
dark the intellectual dark web are
they're challenging the boxes this is
where yeah okay so this is what I want
to kind of take this up to so did you
did you see it was um Ruben just
interviewed Sam Harris did you just see
the way it was like I think couple days
ago yet so this is where I'm nervous
about about their conversation so so so
by the way how intellectual dark web of
you yeah this is where I'm nervous about
their conversation yeah like there's
this conversation going on I want to
bring a hiring something up yeah cuz
when I look at it when I look like when
I look at it and this is where I'm
hoping that I'm hoping that that
Peterson kind of learn from the that
conversation with the guy kind of like
Sam Harris what's his name God they got
Phil hunting which I like easily he's
really cool so I've been following him
for years he's awesome yeah he's really
awesome
um so Sam when he was talking about like
when he was talking about when Reuben
questioned him about like religion and
in in the upcoming of bait Sam said this
thing he's like well I hope we don't get
bogged down in this right but I hope we
get headway and then he laid out his
position my interpretation of what he
said was basically I'm not gonna budge
from this right and I hope I hope that
we can get somewhere here
and what I heard was I hope that Jordan
like can like let that stuff go because
I'm not gonna budge and that's the place
where I'm kind of I'm I'm I'm hoping cuz
there's a way in which I experience Sam
Harris is like there's there's a place
where he's like he's true to the what
we're talking the dark web and that in
that place of like we're gonna engage in
a conversation and work we're engaging
it not to be right and to reaffirm
ourselves right but we're engaging into
it with the explicit risk of being our
world changing after the two of you you
and I interact like the job isn't to win
the debate that his job is to reveal the
truth right Hey and so I give this sense
with religion that there's some there's
something because I think as year is you
really pointed out with with with with
Jordan Peterson he's not at all talking
about religion in the normal American
way that most people think about
religion which is a really like like a a
very shallow like view of it which is
there was this guy named Jesus Christ
who actually lived and they they're
tried to get they look at as an
empirical truth which is a which is
ridiculous right on in that level
Peterson saying that's not the truth
that's revealed in that you're you're
not reading the length the depth of the
language has this history that goes way
way way back and it's the axioms that
you that even Sam Harris is standing on
that's arguing that point for going
against that point is given by the
axioms of judeo christianism right and
so so there's a level of depth and
complexity that I think Jordan Peterson
is trying to bring up with him I don't
know if sam Harris is up to be II I
don't know if he's up to
to letting to letting himself change
that view what what are your thoughts
about that
I just don't I can't see it so here's
what I'll say
unless Jordan becomes more flexible in
creating the frames in which to have the
conversation yep yep right yeah he has
his much chance of getting Sam Harris to
budge from that point yeah
as Michael Eric Dyson has of getting him
to budge from his point about white
privilege that that so let me let me
turn Peterson on himself for a moment
yep
you could say that he's got this entire
framework of myth this hero's journey if
he has brought into the maps of meaning
and he lays out maps meaning is a really
good book very difficult ambitious but
but when it really comes down to it he
does a pretty good job of simplifying
its model down into its essence
fundamental story of of order and chaos
and tyranny in in in danger but also
strength and opportunity and the arrow
articulates that through speech and
action yeah okay so great great story
now he's got this thing about
totalitarianism and gulags and
concentration camps and identity
politics yeah yeah now there is a sense
in which these are deeply connected to
the degree that you play identity
politics you you're on the side of
tyranny in this model yeah right yeah
are par excellence putting people into
boxes and treating them as objects yes
rather than treating them as subjects
yeah you're treating them as members of
a group rather than into
yes and the sequin the sine qua non of
Western civilization as he puts it like
okay you can argue as this western or
whatever is it judeo-christian like he
says that this is built into the Marduk
myth yeah oh yeah okay well that's
that's not judeo-christian well yet yet
right yes we were born in the
judeo-christian thing in the same way
that were born into a Marduk thing right
we're built were born into this heroic
myth as articulated by judeo-christian
somewhat to a degree but at the bottom
of it the thing that he feels is the
defining feature of Western culture is
the recognition that the individual is
the unit of agency and that it is
respect of the individual right in the
in the classic MLK you know the contents
of your character yeah yeah have you
cleaned your room yep what do you bring
to the party when you're when the family
when there's a death in the family how
do you show up for the family like what
do you bring because of who you have
built yourself to be what is your
character what is the fundamental unit
of civilization and he's not willing to
budge right okay Sam Harris is saying
look we have learned to differentiate
through the scientific method which is
reproducible yeah through science
endeavors things we've got the three
strands of valid knowledge right we've
got the injunction a set of instructions
for an experiment first strand second
strand you actually have to perform the
injunction you have to do the experiment
Hey in order to test what the experiment
tests
and rates you have done the experiment
you are now part of what he calls the
community of the adequate right right
right and that is you talk to other
people who have done the experiment and
you check your results against one
another and he simplifies the scientific
method down into this process right and
sam harris is saying look story and myth
can must be interpreted and there are
lots of stories and lots of myths how
come you choose those yeah yeah you
choose those myths or yeah yeah then you
choose to interpret this as
masculine-feminine yeah and you say that
it's in the myth but that's there's a
lot of interpretation going on right and
that way of thinking well the way of
thinking which says that you can't
really know something as fact and as
truth that it's the goal you take that
determines what is truth yeah yeah right
like like I say if you know if you look
around the room you notice what you
notice well but if you look around it as
an interior decorator you're actually
going to notice different things if you
look around the room as an architect
you're gonna notice different things
around the things that exist for you are
a function of your story of your context
of your goal yep okay so goals create
facts and this you could say this is
Jordans fundamental from yep what is
like there's a chunk of goals and goals
creat facts and you can't have a
metaphysics without a goal and that you
can't choose your goal like you can't
like says Oh Ganesha was wrong about
that that is that is an assertion which
requires an argument yes he's made some
good arguments towards that effect yeah
right as Iran would say like reality is
existence is it has a nature it is
is what it is it has an identity right
human beings have an identity we don't
get to choose our ultimate goals we want
life we want health we want beauty we
want intimacy these are built-in we can
attribute those to a god or not we
certainly have been built up in the
stories of that he's unwilling to budge
on the story of the individual hero sam
harris is unwilling to budge on the
distinct nature of science and what it
means to build our stories on science or
not to build them on science both are
fixed unwilling to budge unless they can
create unless they can co-create yeah a
frame that recognizes both of the places
with they're unwilling to budge give
both of them value and then play with
them right right play with them so Sam
why is it so important to you
Jordan why is it so important to you
let's actually find out the value
underneath Sam you've got this
incredible intellect rather than arguing
with him about terms argue with him
about why it's important yeah exactly
you might find that in the end Jordan
backs out of his central conclusion
because whenever he's really pressed one
says there's a peeing game yeah what is
the P shedding game
science empirical data yeah he's saying
there is no secular morality there's
this thing called a pee jetting game
like what the peeing game is secular
morality that's what it is you can't use
that argument and say that you can't
have a secular morality right right
right
totally like now sam harris challenged
him on that ask him how a pata game is
different than a secular morality yeah
yes yeah answer like ask
the questions to get Jordan to actually
are 10 B no one challenges him down to
the core yeah yeah and yeah might when
when you ask him that question he might
have a good answer I haven't heard it
I've been wanting someone to ask him
that question what what's the what's the
question again like if your dad okay so
a PA jetting game as Jordan peterson
says it is okay so if two kids are
playing right you can win the game but
if you win the game in a way that no
one's willing to play with you yeah in
the future then you lose all of the
benefits of playing all the future games
yeah so the strategy of winning at any
cost
yeah is a winning strategy in that game
but you lose the entire iterated set of
games with that person yeah right so
it's win the battle lose the war so you
have to come up with the solution you
have to come up with the strategy that
not only has you win the game but has
you lose sometimes yeah so the peple
will keep playing with you so that you
can get more than the value of winning
the game and this is this is like if we
look at finite and infinite games by
James cars' right a finite game is
played so you get the title of winner an
infinite game is played so that you get
the joy of the continued play so raises
the PSAT and game in Carson terms yeah
right you have to play the game so that
people will continue to play with you
yeah totally
well then it's not just that person you
have to play a game that allows you to
play with all kinds of people because
each each game that you can play with
each of those people offers you value
right right totally and so you have to
play a game that actually creates a
social context yeah in which you can
play more games and if you play games
that make the social context stronger
yeah through time now you've got this
pia jetty in game right a Pia jetty in
game
acts as a selection pressure for the
dominance hierarchy which gets built
into the ultimate player of the
dominance hierarchy namely Jesus in his
and his understanding like Jesus is the
ultimate player of the dominance
hierarchy he is the hero or an one of
the ultimate heroes and he is a pretty
cool hero like okay if you play like
Jesus you're gonna win a lot of
dominance hierarchies Yeah right you're
going to play in such a way that you get
to play with the same person over time
it's play with a lot of people and you
create a context in which people play
with one another because the more people
play with one another the more they have
to bring to you in their games and this
is like the market or you have freedom
and people get to trade according to
their desires they trade with the people
with whom they can play iterated games
through time the market is an iterated
game across players it's a natural Pia
shedding game yeah how can it spin out
of control of course yeah right can you
stop it hmm because iterative organic
games grow around whatever structures
you put in place but that process he's
saying that the ultimate story of how to
navigate status hierarchy or social
hierarchy right that the nature the
feedback mechanisms of the phad and game
hypothesis that framework right explains
how we build up heroes right and those
heroes get encoded into the stories and
those stories get encoded into our
psyche so this pH eddying game serves as
kind of a pressure in natural selection
well we're the people who whose habits
whose character race style of play
allows them to play iterated games with
the same people
integrated games across people games in
other people play with people such that
when they come to your game they bring
more resources Yeah right when you take
those three conditions yeah
they serve as a selection crusher
you're an optimal player yeah an optimal
player gets brought in to stories of
heroes yeah those heroes get selected
for overtime until you get an ultimate
hero such as Jesus Christ such as
Buddha's such as like such as Luke
Skywalker such as obi-wan Kenobi right
right so that ultimate hero
Jordan Peterson calls that religious
okay it's kind of problematical but but
that process is completely secular the
pjt and game is a secular explanation
for morals which is what Piaget said he
wanted to do and Jordan Peterson says PJ
was attempting to create a secular basis
for morality yeah he did such a good job
that whenever I get pressed I use Piaget
nians PJs secular morality explanation
well to justify my quote religious thing
ya know Sam Harris asked him that
question
hey Sam Harris is basically saying look
if we look at if we look at morality we
can look at Piaget T and games right
totally right why why do we want to have
more games
yeah Yeah right and Sam Harris puts it
like he says okay if you want to look
for the ultimate good if we want to say
that there is a natural good in the
universe which does not come from God
but can be rationally explicate 'add and
articulated from analyzing actual lived
experience yeah
he says defining the good is difficult
mm-hmm yeah but defining bad is
relatively easy yeah here says that
Harris says that and he and he offers
three dimensions yeah he says it's the
most
Oh Oh for the greatest number of
creatures for the longest period of time
yeah that's bad if you imagine horrible
suffering for all living beings
throughout time that's the worst
possible outcome right right
in comparison to the worst possible
outcome anything with less suffering for
less creatures over less period of time
is relatively better right right right
right
great that's all the framework we need
to create a secular morality totally and
that's essentially why a PG 18 game
works because if you win I can see if I
can answer so I I still don't know if it
accounts for what is it that cares about
paint that's the thing that's hard to
get underneath I'm not saying that that
makes it fear a lot of logic one so
let's ask the question what is it that
cares about pain yeah okay it's like a
bit like you know it's like it's like
all of life's seems to have that matte
that are more than almost anything right
is name and there is this kind of thing
that the hero what makes the hero the
hero is it volunteers for it on purpose
right it's willing to have pain for the
sake of you know in this case more is
ring the game yeah yeah yes totally tap
for less pain exactly exactly
it seems less pain what is it though can
you create a secular account for this if
then you create a little can you create
a religious account for it you can't
create a religious account for you can't
create a secular account for yes the
universe exists yeah well this is but
this is interesting with this inches
accept so like so so yeah sorry for
cutting now I think that that is what I
think that's what
there's that there's that horizon beyond
the horizons right that we get evidence
for right in the individual caring about
pain and less pain and games and secular
constructs are all in service of like it
presupposes somebody gives a shit about
something yeah it's hard to it's hard to
get under that right the being of being
scared
yes I'm like an amazing the world cares
this is where I think it's like this is
where I think it's like this guy
pseudo-dionysius never heard of him no
oh yeah dude
it's yeah it's basically like it early
early early Christian religion it
basically it's what brings platonic
philosophy into Christmas well it's
actually what brings philosophy like
platonic philosophy into Christianity
thus yeah my origin
like Latinas yeah yeah so it's like that
plots he talks about it basically talks
about a negative theology that there's
and in the French like some of the
French phenomenologist Marion Marion who
wrote the book called God without being
right basically said that like and this
is actually kind of it's interesting
this is where haider going to ended up
to this is what I like about cuz I think
Heidegger is be part of the dark web as
well because he was looking for a
fundamental ontology right that's what
like that's what he was trying to do and
when he wrote being a time right and
that's why I didn't complete it it's
because he's like all right we have not
answered the meat we we have not
explicit ated the meaning of being what
do we mean when we say be me is like
being anti is the thing that you and I
are saying what is it the cares yep
totally okay so - so I I want I want to
get back to that and ask a question
about it yeah
okay so ask answering the question what
is it that cares yeah you're saying that
that's important in some way let's say
that we don't answer that let's say that
we leave that unanswered yeah yeah is
that a problem
well it's it's oh no no I don't think
it's a problem but it's a week it's a
it's a something that to contend with
right like so I'm not like it's it's you
because I've been having this problem
I've been having the same kind of issue
with some of the things when when
Peterson talks about religion right like
a nice he does the thing where he tries
to catch people in the act of valuing
something and he's like well how do you
know basically it's like no the fact
that you know the value that that you
have that goal like has a history and we
can track it down and its mythic and
these the axioms there's a kind of faith
like having axioms is the kind of faith
is how I've heard him talk about that
that that there's something about to
call that God I think is really
problematic to call that even religious
I think it's really problematic yeah so
I actually don't have an answer for it
but okay okay so so for fun what's
interesting though it's also just what's
interesting though is what's bizarre to
me about that is that okay somehow
whatever that is I don't have an answer
for which seems to give constitute how
everything else goes has everything else
go so in some way what is going is
revealing something that is really
mysterious right and there's a pragmatic
approach where it's like with science
when you take the subjectivity out right
which i think is where Sam's coming from
Sam's going like look like I think I
think Peterson would say that like that
science is its side of religion right
and I basically think what he's saying
is that that horizon in the background
that you can't explicitly you can't
explicate scientifically right is
because the thing that gives science
right isn't scientific and I think
that's the basic argument he's trying to
say right but I don't even I don't think
it makes sense to necessarily call that
religious so but he's kind of mystical
okay so so and this is let's take a
postmodern stance of this for a moment
yeah like a rose by any other name
smells just as sweet but what you call
something matters yeah when you call
something religious you are using a word
that has a cachet yeah there was a lot
of meanings behind it yeah so when you
say calling it religious is problematic
right it's problematic in the sense that
it brings in a lot of meanings that
people have a lot of thoughts around and
when you grab that religious you get
people like sam harris saying that's not
religious yeah and now you get into a
semantic set of arguments and that's
what they're doing with this truth thing
okay yes again if you look around the
room as an interior decorator mm-hmm
yeah the things that you notice the
things that matter are completely
different than if you look around the
room as a fire but as an architect like
the things that exist exist in the
context of your goals yeah and so it is
certainly the case that science exists
in the context of a fundamental goal set
which i think sam harris can summarize
very neatly as the desire to avoid
suffering and to go towards the opposite
of suffering
yeah which happens to be extreme
pleasure and beauty and intimacy and
depth and wonder in awe for the most
Yelling's and consciousness over the
longest period of time and we can call
that thriving yeah so you can you can
get the good by examining the bad which
is incontrovertible as as jordan
peterson says life is suffering is the
thing that you can't avoid yeah yeah
great he
and sam harris are in the same boat yeah
and when he says that that is a secular
argument it is not a religious argument
yes it is true that religious figures
have attempted to confront that yeah but
yeah it does not make that realization
religious yeah totally okay but now it's
front using the term religion is front i
think it's fine if you use the word
religion well you just have to make sure
everybody's playing the same game with
the word and he doesn't do yeah I think
that's the whole problem it's a semantic
postmodern problem which he showed
better about bad bad right seems like it
seems like there's got to be a new word
here or something
wait now now I think another way of
bringing in the thing that you said
which is what is it the cares yes yeah
okay now you can take a pan psychic view
of that and say that like everything
that exists exists in relation to
something else
well quarks exist in relationship to
other things atoms and nuclei exist in
relationship that electrons and
electrons and molecules exist in
proteins and cells and beings and
ecosystems they all exist in contexts
and you know Whitehead calls
apprehension yeah right right that
you're actually feeling that which is
you're in relationship to yeah yeah and
that is the precursor of consciousness
right right there's this guy named
Terence Deakin which by the way local
guy Berkeley is the awesome is either
guy that wrote in complete nature yeah
yeah yeah he's cool he's very cool yeah
and and he takes us to a much deeper
level but we can say you can either take
a pan psychic approach and say that all
of nature's is conscious in the sense
that it senses other things that it
exists in the context of other things
and therefore it has to have a way of
connecting to those other things and
that connection is the basis of
consciousness pain psychic approach or
you can say that the nature of
replicating organism
or replicating structures can reach a
point where you get multiple processes
in dynamic tension yeah totally and that
dynamic tension yeah when you get layers
upon layers and orders of magnitude of
these dynamic tensions coming together
create an awareness of how to hold that
structure together and the human
consciousness consciousness in general
and human consciousness in particular is
the awareness of the dynamic structures
as they interplay with one another yeah
totally phenomenological thing built
into the system yeah yeah and how that
relates back to is what is the thing
that cares well in the nature of human
beings and brains and these animals
which are conscious and them this kind
of reflective self-consciousness which
is human in which we have language like
he calls us the symbolic species right
it like we we have language and language
creates a certain kind of dynamic
tension yeah that allows us to abstract
and began to abstract our abstractions
until we can create the self and this is
how we create worlds yeah 3s symbols so
they are a symbolic species yeah
and therefore the reason we care that
which cares is the network of symbols
yep yep yep so in that case it's the
network of symbols that can recognize
that suffering is bad that suffering for
multiple creatures is worse that's
suffering for multiple creatures through
time is the worst we can abstract that
process and therefore we can get a good
we can recognize what it's like to feel
pleasure yeah and that feeling pleasure
across multiple beings and not just
physical pleasure but also mental
pleasure success and joy and and and
spiritual pleasure of realization and
intimacy and appreciation of beauty and
structure and symmetry and
pattern like all of these levels of
pleasure or more beings across time
that's better
we can abstract that we are the symbolic
species that can abstract that what is
that we are that now in a sense I don't
think you need to answer that you know
we have to do a Jordan Peterson move
which is let's just look at what our
culture has decided is good and bad but
let's look at that systematically
scientifically right if there's any
challenge I have what Jordan Peterson is
that he has not done the psycho metrics
of myth well he has not taken all of the
myths and read them through psychometric
tests so that he can pull out and do the
factor analysis yeah I've done that he's
done that intuitively like a case study
yeah yeah totally yeah I think that he
should marry and he should use a
scientific method on the myth so we can
find out what is suffering what is not
suffering and use the collective
knowledge of our culture to figure out
the factors and then figure out what are
the stories that facilitate the
development towards better now it still
doesn't answer how do you determine
better and you can say that that's built
in and that's religious and that there's
an inborn better I like to say reason
requires a reason to use it yeah well
because this word reason has two major
uses one is logic like reason is to be
logical it's to use a set of logical
inferences you use a set of procedures
and iterative procedures to do the
arithmetic to do the math of calculation
for valid conclusions based on right so
there's logic but then there's values
and I go through the difference between
logic and rationality logic has reason
rationality is reason rationality
requires a goal
is it rational to do the thing you have
to do logic but you have to have a goal
right does it lead to the goal then it
is rational to do it to achieve the goal
does it lead away from the goal than it
is irrational might be logical but
irrational right reason requires a
reason to use it there is reason in
terms of logic and reason in terms of
values yeah yeah yeah
Jordan Peterson says it's the values
that determines the logic fan Harrison
says yeah but we use logic to determine
which values are best and yes there is a
spiral but when we get down to it we can
use scientific methods to sort through
the values now Jordan Peterson is doing
that he's just doing it as a case study
instead of psychometrics he hated on the
factor analysis yeah yeah yes bad George
Peterson right totally hey with that I
have to I have to get going okay bye
King this is awesome
[Music]